James Maciukenas, Ph.D.

2 773-290-9947

⋬ blueform@gmail.com

Evanston, IL in www.linkedin.com/in/james-maciukenas

Profile

As a qualitative mixed-methods UX researcher, I worked with some of the biggest names in the tech industry. I specialized in testing generative AI and personas, digital assistants, and search tools to deliver insights driving product decisions and future research.

For over 15 years, I have been teaching science communication to graduate students at the Illinois Institute of Technology (IIT). This grew out of my interest in technical communication and my work sharing the efforts of the faculty of the College of Science at IIT in both print and online mediums.

My diverse background in design, communication, web development, analysis, and teaching has prepared me to tackle complex challenges through research, data gathering, and evaluation.

Experience

UX RESEARCHER, ANSWERLAB, REMOTE & CHICAGO, IL - MAR 2022 - MAR 2024

- Provided insights and findings for design and engineering teams working on generative AI, digital assistants, search, and internal tools.
- Findings led to product decisions and informed future research.

WEB DEVELOPER, INDIANA UNIVERSITY-BLOOMINGTON, IN - AUG 2019 - MAR 2022

- Developed responsive UX standards-based web applications.
- Maintained and enforced ADA accessibility requirements for web applications.

INFORMATION SERVICES, DEPAUL UNIVERSITY, CHICAGO, IL - MAR 2019 - AUG 2019

.NET front-end web design & development to facilitate fundraising.

WEB DEVELOPER & INSTRUCTOR, ILLINOIS INSTITUTE OF TECHNOLOGY, CHICAGO, IL - AUG

- Deliver College of Science student and faculty efforts through websites, newsletters, articles, and event marketing.
- Developed and taught graduate-level science communication course.

CONSULTING, NEWCITY COMMUNICATIONS, CHICAGO, IL - 2015 - 2019

Website development, magazine design and production.

ASSISTANT EDITOR, BUSINESS COMMUNICATION QUARTERLY, CHICAGO, IL - 2006-2013

Review, editing, and preparation of manuscripts for publication.

Education

Illinois Institute of Technology, Chicago, IL – M.S. & Ph.D. in Technical Communication, 2013

References

Available upon request.

Skills

- Science communication
- Public engagement
- Qualitative rapid & embedded research
- Mixed-methods
- In-depth interviews
- **Analysis**
- Insight development
- Report writing
- Discussion facilitation
- Client communications
- Multimedia storytelling
- Data visualization
- Web dev (front)
- Digital and print design

Tools

- **Analytics**
- Adobe CC
- Mural
- dscout
- HTML & CSS
- CMS systems
- Salesforce
- Qualtrics

Personal Skills

- Strong organization skills
- Ability to multi-task
- Attention to detail
- Interpersonal and collaborative
- Self-motivation
- Effective at learning new & emerging tools
- Remote & in-person work ethic